<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
Copyright 2015 Robert A. Beezer

This file is part of MathBook XML.

MathBook XML is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation, either version 2 or version 3 of the
License (at your option).

MathBook XML is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with MathBook XML.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
*********************************************************************-->
<!-- This file was originally part of the book     -->
<!-- (as copied on 2015/07/12)                     -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Abstract Algebra: Theory and Applications   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 1997-2014  Thomas W. Judson     -->

<chapter xml:id="global_wind" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

<!-- % TWJ, 2010/03/31 -->
<!-- % Chapters now begin with Chapter 1 -->

<title>Global circulation and oceanography</title>

<section xml:id="global_winds">
<title>Global wind patterns</title>

<subsection>
<title>Circulation scales</title>

<ul>
<li><term>microscale</term> (&lt;1 km in size): PGF, CEN, friction (cumulus clouds, parcels)</li>
<li><term>mesoscale</term> (1-1000 km): PGF, CEN, friction, Cor (thunderstorms, fronts)</li>
<li><term>synoptic</term> scale (&gt;1000 km): geostrophic balance (mid-latitude cyclones)</li>
<li><term>planetary</term> scale (10,000 km): geostrophic balance (atmospheric circulation cells; prevail over longer timescales)</li>
</ul>

</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="circulation_models">

<title>Circulation models</title>

<ul>
<li><em>model</em>: simplified description of a complex system</li>
<li>used to explain and predict observations using cause-and-effect relationships</li>
</ul>
<p>Any circulation model for the Earth should be able to explain:</p>
<ul>
<li>steady and calm winds observed by mariners</li>
<li>Regions that lack winds</li>
<li>Global patterns of cloudiness</li>
<li>Midlatitude cloud patterns</li>
<li>Global patterns of precipitation</li>
<li>Jet streams</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Global Circulation on Non-Rotating Earth</em></p>
<ul>
<li><em>single cell circulation</em> (Hadley model)</li>
<li>contrast in temperatures between the poles and the equator creates a large convection cell in both hemispheres.</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Global Circulation on Rotating Earth</em></p>
<ul>
<li><p>three-cell circulation: Hadley, Ferrel, and Polar cells</p></li>
<li><p>Coriolis effect deflects flow, poleward flows cool and sink</p></li>
<li><p>Not all cells are <strong>meridional</strong> (N-S motion), there are also <strong>zonal</strong> cells (E-W motion)</p>
<ul>
<li>For example, <em>Walker circulation</em> is the zonal component of a Hadley cell</li>
<li>this behavior is observed in El Nino Southern Oscillation (ENSO)</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</subsection>

</section>


<section xml:id="earth_circulation">
<title>Observed circulation patterns</title>

<p>NOAA Jetstream: <url href="https://www.weather.gov/jetstream/circ"/></p>

<p>Global Circulation Model: Observation</p>
<ul>
<li>tropical <strong>trade</strong> winds converging in <em>Intertropical convergence zone</em> (ICTZ) (region of the <strong>doldrums</strong>)</li>
<li>midlatitude <strong>westerlies</strong> encounter the <strong>polar easterlies</strong> along the <strong>polar front</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><em>Idealized zonal pressure belts:</em></p>
<ul>
<li>The equatorial low is an intertropical convergence zone (ITCZ).</li>
<li>Subtropical highs (STH) are high-pressure zones in the belts about 20°–35° latitude on either side of the equator.</li>
<li>Polar highs near the Earth’s poles are where the polar easterlies originate.</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Monsoons</em></p>
<ul>
<li>seasonal reversal of winds; generally driven by pressure differences.</li>
<li>The Asian monsoon, which affects India and its surrounding areas, China, Korea, and Japan.</li>
<li>The North American monsoon occurs in the southwestern U.S. and northwestern Mexico: this monsoon is driven by the extreme temperatures, which generate a low-pressure center over Arizona and results in a circulation pattern that brings moist air from the Gulf of California and from the Gulf of Mexico, to a lesser degree.</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Cloud and Precipitation</em> patterns also show clear trends related to planetary circulation</p>

</section>

<section xml:id="jet_stream">
<title>The Jet Stream</title>

<p>NOAA Jetstream: <url href="https://www.weather.gov/jetstream/jet"/></p>

<ul>
<li>fast-flowing westerly current flowing between circulation cells</li>
<li>200-250 mbar level, 100-400 mph</li>
<li>essentially driven by geostrophic balance</li>
<li>caused by temperature differences between air near equator and air near the pole</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Seasonal Variations</em></p>
<ul>
<li>migrates depending upon the season (along with other circulation cells)</li>
<li>The polar jet stream is the more prevalent than subtropical jet</li>
<li>It occurs along a major frontal zone, the polar front.</li>
<li>The jet stream moves <em>faster</em> in winter.</li>
<li>tends to migrate southward in the winter</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Rossby Waves</em></p>
<ul>
<li><p>The jet streams meander like rivers, producing a <em>wavelike pattern</em> of troughs and ridges</p></li>
<li><p>The air flow through these waves results in storms that move warm air poleward and cold air toward the equator</p></li>
<li><p>Each trough-ridge combination is called a Rossby wave</p></li>
<li><p>Drift slowly eastward, with rising air near the troughs and sinking air near the ridges</p></li>
<li><p>trough-ridge combinations at 500 mb level and higher</p></li>
<li><p>characterized by <strong>wavelength</strong> and <strong>amplitude</strong></p></li>
<li><p><em>important for development of surface systems!</em></p></li>
<li><p>short waves (&lt;6000 km) may be embedded in long waves</p>
<ul>
<li>smaller-scale disturbances</li>
<li>move relative to longwaves (20-40 mph eastward)</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>


</section>



</chapter>
