<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
Copyright 2015 Robert A. Beezer

This file is part of MathBook XML.

MathBook XML is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation, either version 2 or version 3 of the
License (at your option).

MathBook XML is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with MathBook XML.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
*********************************************************************-->
<!-- This file was originally part of the book     -->
<!-- (as copied on 2015/07/12)                     -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Abstract Algebra: Theory and Applications   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 1997-2014  Thomas W. Judson     -->

<chapter xml:id="oceans" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

<!-- % TWJ, 2010/03/31 -->
<!-- % Chapters now begin with Chapter 1 -->

<title>Ocean-atmosphere interactions</title>

<section xml:id="earth_water">
<title>The Earth's water</title>

<p>The <term>hydrosphere</term> represents the Earth's water inventory, which makes up about 0.03% of the total mass of the Earth. About 97% of this water is found in the oceans, and 3% in freshwater reservoirs. On average, about 0.001% of the Earth's water is present in the atmosphere.</p>

<p>Of the Earth's freshwater inventory (3% of the hydrosphere), most is present in glacial ice (70%) or groundwater (30%), with less than 1% found in surface lakes and rivers. These surface sources thus represent just 0.0003% of the Earth's total water inventory.</p>

<p> From an Earth systems  perspective, it is convenient to divide the water inventory into <term>reservoirs</term> of water with <term>fluxes</term> of material passing between them. This is the basis of the <term>water cycle</term>. The <term>residence time</term> of water in a given reservoir is the size of the reservoir divided by the total outward flux. This provides an indication of how long water resides in each reservoir, or how often this inventory is recycled:</p>
<me>\textrm{residence time} = \frac{\textrm{reservoir}}{\textrm{outward flux}}</me>

</section>

<section xml:id="the_ocean">
<title>The Oceans</title>

<p>From a meteorological perspective, oceans:</p>
<ul>
<li>are the main source of atmospheric water vapor</li>
<li>exchange energy with the atmosphere</li>
<li>transfer heat poleward</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Ocean properties</em></p>
<ul>
<li>71% of the Earth's surface area</li>
<li>Average depth of 3.8 km below sea level(average height of continents is 0.87 km above sea level)</li>
<li>per 100g, contains 3.5g total salt (mostly chlorides with some sulfates)</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Geological context</em></p>
<p>The <term>lithosphere</term> is the uppermost 100 km of the Earth that includes the crust and part of the upper mantle. The Earth is divided into numerous lithospheric plates that can move around relative to each other. In the context of plate tectonics, we find three main types of plate boundaries:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>divergent</em>: plates moving apart from each other. This type of boundary is constructive because new lithosphere must be added at the plate boundary. The best example of this type of boundary are the mid-ocean ridges found throughout the Earth's oceans, where new crust is added via volcanism.</li>
<li><p><em>convergent</em>: plates moving toward each other. This type of boundary is referred to as destructive, because they require a decrease lithospheric plate area. Convergent boundaries can be further subdivided into</p>
<ul>
<li>oceanic-continental: involving the subduction of oceanic lithosphere below continental lithosphere (example: Andes Mountains).</li>
<li>continental-continental: involving the collision of two continental plates. Neither will subduct, leading to mountain formation (example: Himalayas).</li>
<li>oceanic-oceanic: involving the collision of two oceanic plates. Typically, the older and cooler plate will subduct beneath the younger (example: Aleutian Islands)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>transform: plates moving past each other. This type of boundary is referred to as conservative, because lithospheric plate area is neither created nor destroyed at the boundary. The best example of this type of boundary is the San Andreas fault in California.</li>

</ul>

<p><em>Oceanic provinces</em></p>
<ul>
<li>ocean basins may be bounded by active margins (at lithospheric plate boundaries) or passive margines (embedded within a lithospheric plate)</li>
<li>the <term>continental shelf</term> is overlaid by sediment and slopes gradually out to shelf break and the <term>continental slope</term>. At the base of the continental slope is the <term>continental rise</term>.</li>
<li>the <term>abyssal plains</term> are relatively flat depositional surfaces (more common on older ocean floors) and may be dotted with submarine volcanoes.</li>
<li>the <term>mid-ocean ridges</term> are typically found near the centers of the ocean basins (classic example is the Atlantic Ocean) and form the world's largest mountain chains, typically rising 2.5 km above the abyssal plains.</li>
<li><term>trenches</term> are found along active margins where subduction is occurring. Subduction also gives rise to volcanism on the overlying plate, forming a mountain chain such as the Andes Mountains or a volcanic island arc such as the Aleutian Islands.</li>
</ul>

</section>


<section xml:id="ocean_sst">
<title>Ocean temperatures</title>

<p><em>Sea Surface Temperature (SST)</em></p>
<p>The temperature of the ocean is reported as <term>Sea Surface Temperature (SST)</term>, typically measured a 1-3 meters below the surface (but as deep as 20 meters). Three distinct layers can be recognized in the thermal profile of the oceans:</p>
<ul>
<li>the <em>surface zone</em> or mixed layer (top 100 meters) that has the highest temperatures, and the largest variations in temperature as a function of altitude;</li>
<li>the <em>thermocline</em>, a zone of rapidly decreasing temperatures with depth;</li>
<li>the <em>deep zone</em> (below 1000 meters depth) where the temperature is consistently 1-3 C regardless of latittude</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Sea Surface Temperature Anomaly (SSTA)</em></p>
<p> Another measure of ocean temperature is the <term>Sea Surface Temperature Anomaly (SSTA)</term>: which the difference between the nightime SST and the monthly mean nighttime SST based on climate observations over several years. In other words, the SSTA compares the current temperature to "normal" or expected temperatures for a given time of year. Unusually high SSTA values can lead to thermal stress of coral reefs and coral bleaching events.</p>

<p><em>SST patterns</em></p>
<p>A number of persistent SST patterns emerge from ocean observations:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>middle latitudes (and subtropics):</p>
<ul>
<li>western coasts are bordered by cool water</li>
<li>eastern coasts are bordered by warm water</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>tropical latitudes: western coasts bordered by warm water</p></li>
<li><p>polar latitudes: eastern coasts bordered by cold water</p></li>
</ul>
<p>These temperature patterns can be explained by <term>ocean circulation</term> more generally:</p>
<ul>
<li>ocean current patterns generally resemble wind patterns</li>
<li>global-scale wind patterns blow over large regions and push the ocean in the same direction as the wind</li>
<li>a gyre is an ocean circulation that forms a closed loop across an ocean basin; these spin in the same direction as anticyclones, sending warm water poleward and cool water equatorward</li>
<li>winds of subtropical highs tend to cause cold water to flow toward the equator along western coasts</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Ocean currents and the Ekman spiral</em></p>
<ul>
<li>friction between the air and the sea surfaces causes the air to move</li>
<li>the Coriolis effect creates a tendency for the water to veer to the right (in the northern hemisphere) or the left (in the southern hemisphere)</li>
<li>the movement of water influences the next layer of water underneath; this underlying layer will also experience a Coriolis tendency to turn</li>
<li>over the column of water, a pattern emerges in the shape of a spiral</li>
<li>the net result: water tends to move to the right (NH) or left (SH) in Ekman transport</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Circulation and upwelling</em></p>
<p>Ocean currents can act to push surface water toward or away from the coast, which will tend to lead to downwelling or upwelling, respectively. This upwelling plays an important role in primary (biological) production, by bringing cold, nutrient-rich water to surface waters (where photosynthesis can play a larger role).</p>

<p>Good examples of circulation-induced upwelling is along the  coast of California, where cold water moving down the coast has a tendency to veer right (west) and promote upwelling, or the Humboldt current along the west coast of South America, where the cold water moving along the coast has a tendency to veer left (west), promoting upwelling and (under normal conditions) maintaining a westward flow of cold water along the equatorial zone.</p>


</section>

<section xml:id="enso">
<title>El Nino - Southern Oscillation (ENSO)</title>

<p>Climate.gov <url href="https://www.climate.gov/enso"/></p>

<p>The <term>El Nino - Southern Oscillation (ENSO)</term> is an irregular periodic variation in winds and sea surface temperatures over the tropical eastern Pacific Ocean. These variations shift the degree of cold upwelling that occurs along the South American coast, and are connected to larger cycles of periodic warming events connected to global climate.</p>

<p>ENSO conditions are assessed by a range of methods, including</p>
<ul>
<li> SOI (Southern Oscillation Index): the difference in pressure between Tahiti and Darwin, Australia;</li>
<li>the SST and SSTA patterns in the equatorial eastern Pacific</li>
<li>the release of latent heat and outgoing radiation as precipitation patterns shift</li>
<li>monitoring of sea level variations across the equatorial Pacific basin</li>
</ul>


<p><em>Normal ("cold") phase (+SOI)</em></p>
<ul>
<li>upwelling along South American coast</li>
<li>strong trade winds in tropics</li>
<li>high pressures in east-central Pacific (Tahiti &gt; Darwin or +SOI)</li>
<li>cold water moving westward across equatorial Pacific</li>
<li>piling up of water in the western Pacific</li>
<li>dry conditions over east-central Pacific, wet conditions in western Pacific</li>
<li>La Nina can be considered an unusually intense manifestation of this cold phase</li>
</ul>

<p><em>El-Nino ("warm") phase (-SOI)</em></p>
<ul>
<li>downwelling along South American coast</li>
<li>weakened trade winds in tropics (or even some low-level westerly flow)</li>
<li>low pressures in east-central Pacific (Tahiti &lt; Darwin or -SOI)</li>
<li>warm water moving eastward across equatorial Pacific</li>
<li>piling up of water in the eastern Pacific</li>
<li>the entire Walker cell weakens and most eastward</li>
<li>wetter conditions over east-central Pacific, dry conditions in western Pacific</li>
<li>Hadley circulation strengthens; stronger subtropical jet stream</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Global climate and teleconnection</em></p>
<ul>
<li>the changes above influence weather and climate conditions over very large distances. These affects are sometimes referred to as climate <term>teleconnections</term>.</li>
<li>El Nino conditions strengthen the subtropical jet and weaken the polar jet stream. This tends to lead to milder winters in the upper Midwest of the United States, and wetter conditions in the American southwest.</li>
<li>La Nina conditions tend to strengthen the polar jet stream, tending to yield colder and more intense winters in the upper Midwest (i.e. we may find ourselves more often north of the polar front).</li>
</ul>


</section>



</chapter>
